Guide to the James Lippincott Goodwin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Lippincott Goodwin papers
1882-1967
MS 243
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
29.25
(72 boxes, 9 folios, 15 notebooks)
The papers consist of correspondence, business records, maps and records of various forest conservation organizations in Connecticut and North Carolina, where James Goodwin carried on his lumbering operations. His activities in the conservation associations and as field secretary of the Connecticut State Park Forest Commission is documented in correspondence, reports, minutes of meetings and records of plantings carried on by the organizations. The maps show Goodwin's holdings in various parts of Connecticut and Carthage, North Carolina.
Goodwin, James Lippincott, 1881-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. James L. Goodwin, 1969; Emma E. Goggin, 1970; and the Forest History Society, Inc., 1993.
Arrangement
Arranged in thirteen series and one accession: I. Association correspondence, 1917-1967. II. Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association "old" correspondence, 1920-1949. III. Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association "new" correspondence, 1924-1955. IV. Carthage Plantation correspondence, 1927-1959. V. James L. Goodwin "old" correspondence, 1912-1953. VI. James L. Goodwin "new" correspondence, 1928-1967. VII. James L. Goodwin "personal" correspondence, 1882-1967. VIII. Great Pond Nursery and Tree Farm correspondence, 1935-1967. IX. Pine Acres Farm correspondence, 1918-1965. X. Pine Acres Farm, current, 1948-1961. XI. James L. Goodwin business ledgers and records, 1913-1964. XII. James L. Goodwin ledgers, 1928-1965. XIII. Maps included in the James L. Goodwin papers, 1916-1964.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the correspondence, business records surveying field books, and map folios of James Lippincott Goodwin, conservationist, forester, landscape architect, surveyor, philanthropist and patron of the arts. The main body of the records and correspondence commences with 1917 and relates to Goodwin's concern with conservation and the fostering of better forestry principles on the land he had purchased at Clark's Corner, Connecticut, the beginning of Pine Acres Forest. The collection covers the period from 1882, James L. Goodwin's early childhood to his demise in 1967.
James L. Goodwin was born in New York City, in 1881. On his maternal side, he was a member of the Philadelphia Lippincott family of publishing fame. His father, James Junis Goodwin, was a cousin of Junis Pierpont Morgan, Trustee of Groton School, at which school, James L. Goodwin attended, befriended F. D. Roosevelt, and was graduated from in 1900. After attending Yale University and graduating in 1905, James L. Goodwin attended Yale Law School but received his Masters in Forestry in 1910 and became a Private Forestry Consultant. His first marriage to Dorothy Wendell Davis ended on her death in 1945. He was married in 1946 to Genevieve Harlow.
His firm of landscape architects was called James L. Goodwin Associates, Incorporated. He managed his own forest properties at Hampton, Connecticut from 1914 and at Carthage, North Carolina from 1927. From 1913-1914, he was Field Secretary of the Connecticut State Park and Forest Commission. Mr. Goodwin was actively involved in the administration of the Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association and President of the Connecticut Forest and Park Association from 1958-1961. His association correspondence with various conservation groups dates from 1917-1967, (Boxes 1-13).
The Carthage correspondence (Boxes 14-16) illustrates Mr. Goodwin's perception in choice of lieutenants for his timber operations. In 1927 when James L. Goodwin initially attempted to purchase Colin G. Spencer's Moore County, North Carolina land, sight unseen, Mr. Spencer declined but eventually agreed to the sale of 200 acres. Gradually, a total of 1,100 acres was purchased at Carthage, by Colin Spencer for Mr. Goodwin's forest experiment. Mr. Spencer's management of Carthage Plantation was to their mutual benefit. While James Goodwin financed the forestry operation and advised better forestry practices, Colin Spencer supervised the planting and improved cutting of the trees and was the sole customer for the timber taken from the tract. Mr. Spencer served as President of the North Carolina Forestry Association and as a director of the American Forestry Association.
Harold H. Sweeton, Forester of Great Pond Forest, and James L. Goodwin supervised the Simsbury operation so well that in 1956 Great Pond Forest was deemed Tree Farm number one in Connecticut by the American Tree Farm System. (Boxes 23-30).
The chief value of these papers lies in the meticulous recording of forest and farm operations. In the words of a staff member of the United States Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, "We are deeply impressed by your Pine Acres operation and by the infinite degree of management and attention that Mr. Stocking has given this property. His detailed records of input and output by compartment and sub-compartment is something to be admired. We believe that his emphasis on the production of quality forest products is sound and his success in marketing these products, a phase on which many forest owners stumble, is exceptional." This statement should be extended to Mr. Sweeton's work at Great Pond Nursery and Forest and Mr. Spencer's at Carthage Plantation. There are twenty-six ledgers (L1-L26) and sixty-one manuscript boxes (41-101) containing records of Annual Reports, Farm Accounts, Farm Labor Accounts, Man Labor Records, Payroll Note-books and Timber Records, and Work-sheets from 1913-1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
James Lippincott Goodwin was an architect, forester, and conservationist. He received a masters degree in forestry from Yale University in 1910 and became a private forestry consultant, as well as a landscape architect. From 1913-1914, Goodwin was field secretary of the Connecticut State Park and Forest Commission. He served as president of the Connecticut Forest and Park Association from 1958-1961. The following paragraphs on Goodwin are taken from History of the Class of 1905, Yale College Volume X, page 58.
James Lippincott Goodwin: Secretary-treasurer, Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association, 15 Lewis Street, Hartford, Conn.; residence, 10 Woodside Circle, Hartford.
"My chief interests," Goodwin says, "are the management of my forest tract of 1,700 acres in the Town of Hampton, Windham County, Conn. From a small beginning this has grown and developed since 1914. It has been interesting to watch trees planted twenty or thirty years ago grow to merchantable size which now can be cut and from which there is an appreciable income. In 1951 I compiled and wrote an illustrated history of its development, entitled Pine Acres Forest, from 1914 to 1952. I also own a tract of 1,000 acres in Moore County, near Pinehurst, N.C. On account of the fast growth of Southern pines, this has been a very successful business enterprise since 1930.
After serving for some years as a director of the Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Goodwin is now president of the organization. He is a member of the committee of the Hartford Y.M.C.A. camps property committee, a trustee of Trinity College and the Wadsworth Atheneum Art Museum, and a member of the Chapter of Christ Church Cathedral. He is also serving as vice-president of the Society for the Protection of New Hampshire Forests, is a senior fellow of the Society of American Foresters, and belongs to the Massachusetts and North Carolina Forestry associations, the Connecticut Historical Society, the Connecticut Antiquarian and Landmarks Society, and the New York Yale Club.
His first wife, Dorothy Wendell Davis, died in December, 1945, and in November, 1946, he was married in New York City to Genevieve Hancock Harlow.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forest conservation; Forests and forestry; Lumbering -- Connecticut; Lumbering -- North Carolina; Connecticut; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; Businessmen; Conservationists; Foresters; Goodwin, James Lippincott, 1881-1967; Connecticut. State Park and Forest Commission; Yale University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies -- Students
- Association correspondence, 1917-1967; Series I
  - American Forestry Association, 1923-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Patrol member certificate to James L. Goodwin, 1923; 1942 request by James L. Goodwin to have Colin G. Spencer appointed as Director of AFA honored by Spencer's nomination on the ballot; 1944 correspondence between James L. Goodwin and William P. Wharton explaining the AFA Forest Appraisal Project; 1965 AFA publication, "Teaching Conservation, A Guide to Natural Resources", order for 30 copies to be donated to Hartford Board of Education.
  - Audubon Societies, 1917-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    James L. Goodwin elected as member of the Amston Game Club; 1942 brochure description of the Club; 1930 Agreement between members of the Club and the Hartford Connecticut Trust Company; 1933 dissolution of the Club; J. L. Goodwin membership in Florida Audubon and National Audubon Societies.
  - Connecticut Christmas Tree Growers Association, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Dues notice and Membership Cards for J. L. Goodwin.
  - Connecticut Forest Industries Committee, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Recreation and forest industry lands with proposed industry plans.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Committee, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    James L. Goodwin as Chairman of the Sub-Committee on State Parks has correspondence with members of the committee; Report on State Forests and Parks; Objectives of the Policy and Program Committee to guide Directors on present activities of the Association, private forestry, forest fire control, and state forests and parks.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Articles for Connecticut Woodlands by James L. Goodwin including "Forest Protective Associations in Connecticut", "Forestry in Eastern Connecticut", and "The Latvians at Pine Acres Farm".
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and various officials of the Association including Edward M. Bradey, Trustees of the Permanent Fund of the Association, regarding funds and investments plans; Edgar L. Heermance, Secretary of the Association, and Harold K. English presenting Budget Report and Report of the Permanent Trust Fund.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Marketing Committee, 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1932 Report of Marketing Committee Meeting; Report by Edgar L. Heermance for Governor Baldwin, "Brief on Fuelwood Utilization"; correspondence concerning experimentation in handling and processing of fuelwood.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association Meetings, 1943-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1943, 1948, 1949, 1950 Minutes of Directors Meetings; 1945, Articles of Incorporation; Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Harold E. Conroy, Member of Connecticut General Assembly, urging legislation to give State Forester and Superintendent of Parks greater responsibility; 1947 Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Governor James L. McConaughy regarding floating a Bond for state parks; 1950, Activities program; Bulletins offering scholarships to conservation workshops and measures in the prevention of Dutch Elm disease.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association Members, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Various Association lists including 1933 Contributors and Life Members, Hartford section; 1938 Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association list, and 1936 List of Life Members of Connecticut Forest and Park Association.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Miscellaneous and Meetings, 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with William C. Shepard, Secretary and Forester of Association, appointing James L. Goodwin to Legislative Committee; 1949 Brochure of Spring Field Meeting held at Pine Acres Forest; Speech by William Wharton, Massachusetts, Forest and Park Association, at this field meeting; 1950- List of Nominating Committee.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Northeastern Wood Utilization Council, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Minutes of Meeting of Council, 1943, 1944; Bulletins: Report of Progress 1942-1946; Acknowledgement of James L. Goodwin's contributions; Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Edgar L. Heermance, Secretary of Northeastern Wood Utilization Council.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association Public Relations, 1936-1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    James L. Goodwin correspondence on behalf of the Association with members of Connecticut General Assembly and the United States Congress urging in 1937 that the General Assembly issue a Bond for State Forest and Land Purchase; H. R. 6914 Bill, "To stimulate acquisition, development and proper administration of state forests in coordination with Federal activities;" 1939 Connecticut Forest and Parks in New England; 1938 article by H. H. Chapman, "Shall our State Parks be Self-Supporting"; 1943 contribution by James L. Goodwin for the purchase of William Gillette Estate as a State Park.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, Talcott Mountain Trail, 1934-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    1934 Route Map of proposed Talcott Mountain Trail between Connecticut and Farmington Rivers; Hartford Trail Section, in correspondence with Edgar L. Heermance, Chairman Trails Committee, and various property owners setting standards for fire protection and gaining permission for trail rights; Directive for use of trails.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1937-1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Routine Association matters such as Minutes of Directors Meeting and letters of solicitation; Correspondence and publications about areas of legislative concern; Protection of highways; Studies of Park and Forest Commission; Concern that President Roosevelt does not transfer the United States Forest Service from the Department of Agriculture to the Department of the Interior.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15a)
    Report of meetings; Correspondence between Association President, Walter Howe and Governor Bowles about conservation.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1951, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence between J. L. Goodwin and W. C. Shepard, Association Secretary and A. W. Hurford, Secretary and Forester, regarding such Association activities as notices, bulletins, Minutes of Directors Meeting, Budget Reports and subsidizing Connecticut Woodlands.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 16a)
    1952 Association Membership list; News-clipping on Dinosaur National Park's proposed dam; Article and photographs by Katherine Boyd, "Goodwin Land Presents Conservation Policies".
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Correspondence between J. L. Goodwin and National Legislators Bush, Albert, Dodd and Harrison concerning opposition by Mr. Goodwin to the flooding of the Dinosaur National Park Canyon; Correspondence between Mr. Goodwin, Chairman of Forestry Committee and President Walter Howe directing Mr. Goodwin to initiate a Tree Farm System in Connecticut.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Routine Association matters such as Budget Report, Minutes of Directors Meeting and service on Nominating Committee; Correspondence with Richard Goodwin, Director of Connecticut Arboretum of Connecticut College regarding the Fund to preserve Mamacoke Island, on the Thames River, as a Wilderness Area; Correspondence with various state and national legislators regarding opposition to construction of a dam in Dinosaur National Park; Maintenance of a National Arboretum in Washington, D. C.; Proper uses of insecticides.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Correspondence between President James L. Goodwin and members of the Association concerning Association business such as filling Board of Directors positions, soliciting funds and acknowledging them; Budget Report and Meeting Agenda; Report of permanent Trust Fund by Treasurer, W. O. Filley and President Report; Copy of letter from H. H. Chapman to Governor Ribicoff citing procedures for an effective State Park and Forestry Association.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Correspondence between President Goodwin and Secretary Forester, A. W. Hurford, regarding such Association business as notice of Meetings, Minutes of Meeting of Board of Directors, Budget Reports and solicitation and acknowledgment of funds; Letters and reports to various state and national administrators and legislators pertaining to areas of conservation, rigid Federal standards for bill-boards along highways, and use of selected inmates of Cheshire Reformaty as maintenance workers on State Parks and Forests.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Correspondence relating to Association business between President Goodwin and Secretary and Forester, A. W. Hurford; Association Articles of Incorporation, 1928 and By-Laws as amended, 1948; Progress Report of Connecticut Natural Areas Program; Report by Raymond Kienholz, "The Forests of Connecticut"; Strong recommendation by Association for Work Camp Program of carefully screened juvenile offenders.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Correspondence between President Goodwin and Secretary and Forester Hurford relating to Association administration; Correspondence concerning such policy items as opposition to relocation of Watertown Thruway through Black Rock State Forest; Opposition to the use of gift lands by the state for other than the intended purpose and letter to Governor Ribicoff opposing the creation of a Department of Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, January-May, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Correspondence of Association business such as notices and Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings and Budget Reports; Controversy over the use of land area dedicated to Park use for Highway Construction is presented to Governor Ribicoff and the Association opposition made known.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, June-December, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 23a)
    Correspondence about the rights of the Highway Department to encroach on State Forest and Park land with Milton P. DeVane reporting on the power of eminent domain; Use of Herbicides in controling undesirable vegetation along town roadsides.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Mr. Goodwin's resignation as President, and Roger Eddy election as President of the Association; Included are Minutes of Board of Directors Meeting, Budget Reports, and Presidents Annual Report.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Routine Association business such as Budget Reports, Board of Directors Meetings, and contribution by James L. Goodwin to Connecticut Woodlands
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Routine Association business including Statement of Operating Fund; Report of Treasurer and correspondence with Association President H. W. Baker, Jr.,; Brochure stating aims and operation of the James L. Goodwin Conservation Center in Hampton and Chaplin Connecticut.
  - Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Routine Association business such as Budget Reports, Treasurer Reports; Included are the Recommendations by the Association to the Governor's Conference on Natural and Environmental Beauty; Acknowledgment of Mr. Goodwin's $25,000 to the fund.
  - Connwood, Incorporated, 1945-1962 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and the Officers of Connwood, an organization of Connecticut Timber Owners for the marketing of Forest Products; Edgar L. Heermance, Secretary, Treasurer, 1946; Mr. Goodwin discusses such matters as stock subscriptions, Articles of Incorporation and a 1947 Pulpwood Operation Agreement; Included are Annual Reports for 1954-1956, 1959-1960; In 1962 Connwood is converted into an organization to provide professional forestry services to forest owners of Connecticut, Rhode Island, and Massachusetts.
  - Miscellaneous Association, 1939-1966 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Publication, "The American Tree Farm", and literature of the Aiken County Forest Protective Association.
  - New England Forestry Foundation, 1944-1950 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Correspondence between Mr. Goodwin and Harris A. Reynolds, Secretary of Foundation; Notices of Annual Meeting, Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings, and acknowledgment of financial gift by James L. Goodwin.
  - Society of American Foresters, 1925, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Routine association business folder including 1928 membership list; Brochure on the Policy of the Association; Notices of Meetings; 1930-1931 Report on the Protection of Roadside Beauty.
  - Society for the Protection of New Hampshire Forests, 1924-1927 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Correspondence between Mr. Goodwin and Philip W. Aires, Forester of the Society, including a concern to save Franconia Notch from commercialism; 1939 New Hampshire Legislative Bill to conserve the public interest in forest lands and the contribution by James L. Goodwin to the movie produced by the Society, "New England Trees For You".
- Talcott Mountain Forest Protective Association "old" correspondence, 1920-1949; Series II
  - Alsop, J. W. Survey, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    J. W. Alsop, First Selectman of the Town of Avon agreeing to the employment of a watchman by the Association.
  - Annual Meetings-Minutes, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Minutes of Annual Meetings; Revised 1935 Constitution of the Association and a Statement of Purpose.
  - B, 1931-1939 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with W. E. Britton, Superintendent, Connecticut Geological and Natural History Survey, regarding Entomological Survey; Paul Butterworth regarding infested red pine; and other members of the Association concerning routine business such as assesment for work done and dues collection.
  - Black Ledge Forest Protective Association, 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with individual interested in initiating a protective forest association in eastern Connecticut including a list of applications for membership in the Black Ledge Forest Protective Association.
  - C, 1929-1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    General Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Horace B. Clark regarding such issues as advice on forestry work for property and administration of the Association.
  - Circular Letters-Fire, 1925-1937 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Correspondence includes Permits for Kindling Fires and circular letters to the members of the Association regarding methods of fire prevention.
  - Circular Letters-General, 1924-1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Correspondence to the membership of the Association including Notices of Annual Meetings; Protective legislation, services available to the Membership; clear-cutting provision requested by the State Forestry Department and ways to relieve the fuel shortage.
  - Circular Letters-Planting, 1926-1941 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Circular letters sent to James L. Goodwin, Secretary, to the members of the Association on the subjects of planting evergreen trees under the Clark-McNary Law, and lists of types of trees available for planting.
  - Conservation Corps Work, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 9)